<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
	<body>
	
	  <release version="1.18.0-rc1" date="2023-04-19" description="Feature release with compression fixes and many improvements.">
	    <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="377">
	      Fixed use of ZDITHER0 keyword to restore or record random generator seed when dithering is used in (de)compression.
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="349">
	      Fixed tiled (de)compresssion of some quantized images via GZIP.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="at88mph" issue="387">
	      Added ability to stride while tiling.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="at88mph" issue="356">
	      Added ability to stream image cutouts.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="at88mph" issue="400">
	      Added ability to stream compressed image cutouts.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="at88mph" issue="352">
	      Added support for alternative RandomAccess immplementations.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="335">
	      Added NullDataHDU for more intuitive support for header only HDUs with no associated data.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="207">
	      Unified deferred read implementation for all Data classes.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="395">
	      Consistent behavior and method visibilities across Data subclasses.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="209">
	      FitsUtil.reposition() deprecated and changed to take FitsIO argument to match usage.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="394">
	      Various tweaks to FitsDate that should not affect user behavior.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="336">
	      Deprecate unsafe methods that should only be used internally (if at all) and never by users.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.17.1" date="2023-03-15" description="Maintenance release with critical bug fixes.">
      <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="368">
	      Fixed first extension written as primary if primary HDU contained no data (affects 1.17.0).
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="367">
	      Fixed incorrect checksum calculated directly from file in multi-HDU FITS, and other checksum fixes (affects 1.17.0).
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="keastrid" issue="341">
	      Fixed occasional NullPointerException in tiled image compression resulting from incomplete initializiation of TiledImageCompressionOperation.
      </action>
	  <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="373">
	      Fixed GitHub Actions site build error, by removing unused broken dependency from POM.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="376">
	      Upload coverage report to Coveralls.io also (forks need to set a repo token via the repo secret COVERALLS_REPO_TOKEN if want to
	      enable reporting also).
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.17.0" date="2022-09-11" description="Improved image compression, checksum support, and incremental writing">
      <action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="319">
	      Generalized tile compression for any-dimensional images based on the FITSIO convention. 
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="318">
	      Fixed broken tile compression of non-square images. 
      </action>
      <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="318">
	      CompressedImageHDU.fromInageHDU() now defaults to tiling by row if tile size is not explicitly specified, as per FITS specification and also for consistent behavior in higher dimensions.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="266">
				Safe incremental HDU writing via new FitsOutput interface, which is used to check whether HDUs should be set 
				primary or not depending on where it is located in the output.
			</action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
	      Simpler, faster, and more versatile FitsChecksum class, with support for incremental checksum updates, checksum retrieval, and checksum computations directly from files.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
	      New checksumming methods: BasicHDU.calcChecksum(), .setChecksum(), .getStoredChecksum(), and .getStoredDataSum(); Data.calcChecksum(); Fits.calcChecksum(int) and .setChecksum(int) -- as well as an extended static API for `FitsCheckSum`.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="328">
	      Checksum in-memory headers/data with less overhead through piped streams.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
        Fits.setChecksum(), .setCheckSum(int), and .calcChecksum(int) compute checksum directly from the file, if possible, for 
        deferred read data (i.e. data not currently loaded into RAM). This eliminates the need to keep 
        potentially huge data volumes in RAM when computing or updating checksums in an existing FITS file.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
        Fits.setChecksum() will now checksum all HDUs, including those not already loaded from disk -- 
        keeping data in deferred read mode if possible.
      </action>
      <action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
        Added Fits.rewrite() to simplify re-writing the entire Fits objects, e.g. after updating checksums. The 
        implementation is efficient in that it skips data segments in deferred read mode. BasicHDU.rewrite()
        is modified to make it efficient also.
      </action>
    	<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="283">
	      User adjustable header comment alignment position via Header.setCommentAlignPosition(int) and checking via .getCommentAlignPosition(). 
      </action>
    	<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="145">
				New Fits.getHDU() methods to select HDU from Fits by name (and version).
			</action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="311">
        Duplicate header keys, during parsing, are repoted though separate logger instance from Header's, with verbosity
        controlled via Header.setParserWarningsEnabled(boolean). 
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="292">
        Suppress repeated duplicate keyword warnings when parsing and improve checks for FITS standard violations. Added Header.getDuplicateKeySet() method to check which keywords have duplicates. 
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="292">
        Replacing header keys logs a warning when existing value type is incompatible wth the newly associated 
        standardized keyword.
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="292">
        Creation of header entries with standardized keywords logs a warning if associated value type is incompatible 
        with the keyword. 
      </action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="292">
        Improved header card ordering implementation.
      </action>
  		<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="323">
	      Added Data.isDeferred() method (defaulting to false) that can be used to check if a FITS Data 
	      object might be in deferred read mode, that is if it may not be fully loaded into RAM. Note, that while 
	      the method is properly implemented for the built-in data types of the library, it may not properly reflect 
	      the deferred status of external data implementations unless these override the method with something 
	      meaningful also.
      </action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="74">
        New logo.
			</action>
	  </release>
	  
	  <release version="1.16.1" date="2022-03-21" description="Maintenance release with bug fixes.">
	    <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="252">
				Fixed broken Java 8 compatibility of 1.16.0 due to Java compiler flags in POM. Note, after the change the build itself will require Java 9 or later!
			</action>
	    <action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="243">
				Fixed potential unchecked null in BinaryTableHDU.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="257">
				No Logger warnings about duplicate header cards if Header parser warnings are disabled.
			</action>
      <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="210">
				Added default ArrayDataInput/Output implementations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="229">
				Removed runtime dependency on javax.annotation-api.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="dependabot">
				Mostly automated updates of dependencies.
			</action>
	  </release>
	
	  <release version="1.16.0" date="2021-12-13" description="Compliance to FITS 4.0 standard, plus many more fixes and improvements.">
	    <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="197">
	      This release contains numerous API changes and additions. While the source code is generally back-compatible with previous versions of this library for compiling, some method signatures have changed, and as a result the JAR should not be used as a drop-in replacement for applications that were compiled against earlier versions. To use version 1.16.0 of this library you should always compile your application against it.
	    </action>
	    <action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="161">
				Long strings enabled by default (FITS 4.0 standard).
			</action>	
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="195">
				Permissive default 'FitsFactory' settings: error-free reading of some flawed 3rd party files by default (as long as they can be made sense of). However, issued encountered with 3rd party FITS files are logged so they can be inspected. Added new 'FitsFactory.setDefaults()' method to restore default settings more easily.
			</action>	
			<action type="update" dev="olebole" issue="125">
				Set 'FitsFactory.useHierarch(true)' by default. HIERARCH style keys are written upper-case only by default, but case-sensitive support can also be enabled via a call to the 'setCaseSensitive(boolean)' method of the 'IHierarchKeyFormatter' instance used by 'FitsFactory'.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="177">
				Added support for preallocated blank header space, as per FITS 4.0 standard. via 'Header.ensureCardSpace(int)' and 'Header.getMinimumSize()'. Headers remain rewritable in-place as long as they don't exceed their original size in the file.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="172">
				Added support for complex values in FITS headers, as specified by the FITS standard, via new 'ComplexValue' class.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="167">
				Added support for header integers in hexadecimal format, as specified by the FITS standard, e.g. via 'addHexValue(...)' and 'getHexValue(...)' methods in both 'Header' and 'HeaderCard' classes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="171">
				Prevent the creation of invalid header entries from code, by throwing informative runtime exceptions. New runtime exception classes 'HierarchNotEnabledException', 'LongStringsNotEnabledException', 'LongValueException', 'UnclosedQuoteException' are used to report when illegal action was pre-empted relating to FITS headers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="165">
				Prevent creating header cards with NaN and Infinite values. The FITS standard does not support these.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="169">
				More predictable explicit precision control for header decimals. The same number of decimal places are shown after the leading figure regardless whether fixed-decimal or scientific (exponential) notation is used.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="wcleveland" issue="120">
				Added optional support for using 'D' instead of 'E' as the exponent in decimal representations (via 'FitsFactory.setUseExponentD(boolean)' setting), as specified by the FITS standard.  
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="173">
				Fully preserve long comments for string values, including internal spaces in the comment, using the now standard long string convention.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="170">
			  Simpler, better methods for adding creating comment and history entries in headers, such as via 'Header.insertComment(String)' or '.insertHistory(String)', or via 'HeaderCard.createCommentCard(String)' or '.createHistoryCard(String)'.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="170">
			  'Header.addValue(...)' and 'Header.insert...(...)' methods now return the newly created 'HeaderCard' objects for convenience.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="121">
				More predictable header card ordering when editing headers, both directly or indirectly via an iterator. 
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="192">
				New FITS IO class hierarchies for better layering and separation of functionality. Standard IO functions (for reading, writing, positioning, and skipping) now conform to their canonical contracts in the core Java API. The messy old IO API is also supported, though deprecated, to provide back compatibility until the next major release. The new IO classes are also 2 to 3 times faster than before. 
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="188">
				'FitsHeap' access made a lot more efficient with true random access.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="187">
				No 'EOFException' is thrown when skipping beyond the end of file, since it should be allowed in random access mode.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="186">
				Consistent handling of logical ('true'/'false') values in FITS binary tables, including newly added support for 'null' (or undefined) values also as per FITS standard.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="184">
				In prior versions 'char[]' arrays in binary tables were written as 16-bit Unicode and read back as 'short[]' integers. FITS recognises only ASCII character arrays with 1-byte per character. A new 'FitsFactory.setUseUnicodeChars(boolean)' option can toggle compliance to the FITS standard for 'char[]' arrays. However, the misconceived prior behavior remains the default to maintain back compatibility until the next major release. 
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="182">
				Replace fragmented 'PrimitiveType...' hierarchy with a more aptly named one-stop 'ElementType' class. The old hierarchy is also available, albeit in deprecated form.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="191">
				Type safe BITPIX values via new 'Bitpix' enum providing a restricted set. The unsafe BITPIX methods have been deprecated for removal in a future release.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="attipaci" issue="175">
				Added new 'Header.setParserWarningsEnabled(boolean)' option to log FITS standard violations when reading (3rd party) headers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="153">
				no more 'Logger' warnings on multiple CONTINUE keywords, tolerant HIERARCH parsing, and other small fixes.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="FinitePhaseSpace" issue="138">
				'FitsDate' equals() / hashCode() / compareTo() implementations.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="Zlika" issue="135">
				Fix management of sub-seconds in 'FitsDate'
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="olebole" issue="130">
				Check for and reject non-ASCII or non-printable characters in headers. The FITS standard allows only ASCII characters in the range of 0x20 to 0x7E in the headers. The new static method 'HeaderCard.sanitize(String)' is available to users to replace characters outside of the supported range with '?'. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="wcleveland" issue="123">
				Minor fixes prior to release
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="attipaci" issue="164">
				Source code updated for Java 8, with diamond operators and try-with-resources used throughout as appropriate.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="162">
  			Revised when exceptions are thrown, and they are made more informative by providing more essential details and traceable causes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="159">
  			HIERARCH header cards are now written to conform to 'cfitsio' specification, which requires a space before '='. While the HIERARCH convention itself does not specify the extra space, it certainly allows for it, and with the change our FITS files shall be more conformant to, and readable, by yet another widely used library.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="mbtaylor" issue="158">
				Check for 'markSupported()' when attempting to use 'mark()' or 'reset()' methods in 'ArrayDataInput', and throw an appropriate runtime exception if the methods are not supported by the implementation.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="156">
				Fixed issues with handling of single quotes as part of user-supplied strings.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="mbtaylor" issue="143">
				"I10" format ASCII tables are parsed as 32-bit 'int[]' by default (for back compatibility), unless 'TLMIN/TLMAX' or 'TDMIN/TDMAX' header entries indicate a more extended range. Added new 'AsciiTable(Header, boolean)' constructor to optionally change the preference to read "I10" ASCII table data as 64-bit 'long[]' columns.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci" issue="190">
				Changed to generated serialVersionUIDs from 1L for classes that require it.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci">
				Various smaller fixes and improvements throughout, increased unit test coverage, and more comprehensive unit tests.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="attipaci">
	      Deprecated classes and methods that (a) were exposed in the public API even though they should not have been, (b) had names that poorly reflected their function, (c) were poorly conceived/designed in the first place, and/or (d) were prone to misuse with unpredictable results. The deprecated API remains supported nonetheless, and slated for removal in the next major release (2.0) only.
			</action>
	    <action type="fix" dev="attipaci">
	      A lot of the Javadoc API documentation has been revised and improved.
			</action>
	  </release>
	  
		<release version="1.15.2" date="2017-04-28" description="Maintenance release with bug fixes.">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with bug fixes.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="113">
				Header can be controlled to specify the header card order.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="112">
				ImageHDU tiler corrupts values after 2GB worth of data bug fixed.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="108">
				Non standard BITPIX allowed during de/compression. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="107">
				Add tiler support for ImageHDU from uncompressing a CompressedImageHDU?
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="106">
				Remove redundant spaces in HIERARCH keys .
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="105">
				Fix integer overflow in case of negative values in combination with a defined blank value of Integer.MIN_VANUE.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="104">
				make the worker threads deamons so they do not hold of a shutdown enhancement.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="98">
				Update Outdated documentation in introduction enhancement, thanks to MaxNoe.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="90">
				Fix Reading boolean arrays with getColumn bug.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.15.1" date="2016-08-19" description="Maintenance release with bug fixes.">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with bug fixes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="102">
				Comment type header cards where not protected against to long comments, that can result in corrupted headers. 
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="MaxNoe" issue="101">
				Introduction document verified and corrected kind thanks to Maximilian Nöthe. 
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.15.0" date="2016-08-07" description="Table compression activated.">
			<action type="update">
				Binary table compression and tiling are now fully supported by nom-tam-fits. An API for easy handling of compressed tables is now provided.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="61">
				Binary table compression now fully supported.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="70">
				The dummy compression algorithm NOCOMPRESS is now supported.
			</action>
			<action type="update" issue="96">
				Multiple code quality fixes, provided by various developers.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.14.3" date="2016-06-05" description="Maintenance release with minor bug fixes.">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with bug fixes.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="92">
				 Removal of redundent attribute "rowSize". Attention here the public api has a minor change, the deletColumns in the ColumnTable does not return an int anymore.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="91">
				 Fix for a bug in encurling the multim arrays of the BinaryTable with variable length columns.
			</action>
	    </release>
		<release version="1.14.2" date="2016-03-11" description="Maintenance release with minor bug fixes and enhancements.">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with important bug fixes and the restoration of java 6 support.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="84">
				Fits does not handle comments that start with 8 blank characters correctly when reading/writing/reading bug .
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="80">
				Restored Java 6 compatibility. 
			</action>
	    </release>
		<release version="1.14.1" date="2016-02-24" description="Maintenance release with minor bug fixes and enhancements.">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with minor bug fixes and enhancements.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="79">
				Important note for all users, since 1.13.0 a bug is fixed in the table behavior. This can cause problems for users expecting the "buggy" result. See the issue on github for more details.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="77">
				Since a approximately 1.12.0 nom-tam-fits uses java.util.logging for all logs, the details what and where to log to can therefore be configured freely.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="76">
				In case of long strings the difference between a null comment and an empty string was not detected correctly.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="60">
				Image compression support for the null pixel mask, this allows correct NaN with the use of lossy compression's.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.14.0" date="2016-01-10" description="full Image compression support">
			<action type="update">
				Image compression and tiling are now fully supported by nom-tam-fits. A 100% Java implementation of the compression libraries available in cfitsio
				was implemented. An API for easy handling of compressed images is now provided. Support for binary table compression and the NULL_PIXEL_MASK features is
				anticipated in the next release.
			</action>
			<action type="update">
				When [de]compressing all available CPU's are automatically utilized.
			</action>
			<action type="update">
				Internal compression allows FITS files to be created where the data are efficiently stored, but the
				metadata is still easily accessible. The tiling of images is particularly critical
				for supporting efficient access to subsets of very large images. A user can easily access
				only the tiles that overlap the region of interest and can skip data not of interest.
				While some skipping might be possible with uncompressed FITS files (i.e., read only the rows
				overlapping the desired
				subset), internal tiles can be much more efficient when the image is
				substantially larger than the subset. Most compression algorithms interfere with the ability to
				skip uninteresting data, but tiles are compressed independently, so users can benefit both from
				the compression and the selection of only a subset of the image.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="48">
				Added a [de]compression API supporting all compression methods in the proposed updates
				to the FITS standard.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="26">
				Wrong checksum calculation corrected.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="54">
				Some problems with data segments that are bigger than 2GB corrected.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="62">
				Header parsing performance optimization.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="68">
				Comment style cards with a empty key value can now be used multiple times.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="68">
				Alignment of hierarch headercard values deactivated.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="72">
				The formatting of hierarch card keys can mow be be controlled. Two formats are provided.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.13.1" date="2015-08-21" description="Maintenance release with fixes for hierarch/longstring and rewrite bugs">
			<action type="update">
				Maintenance release with fixes for hierarch/longstring and rewrite bugs.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="46">
				After the correction of #44 the padding calculation of the fits header was wrong, now the calculation is consistent.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="44">
				Improved the calculation of the number of cards to be used for a longstring in case of a hierarch
				cards because it was wrong when some special string lengths where used. Now rewriting is useing the
				new calculation to see if the header fits in place.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="43">
				More variants of the hierarch keywords as in #16.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="16">
				More variants of the hierarch keywords allowed (lowercase and dot), but writing will convert the keywords back to the standard.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.13.0" date="2015-07-17" description="This is a stability release, before the new fits standard will be implemented in version 2.0">
			<action type="update">
				Major updates to the util package including a set of routines for efficient
				copyying of arrays of all types. Some of the special FITS values are
				collected in the FitsIO class. New buffering utility classes have also been created.
				Some methods that were public in the util package but which were not used in
				the FITS library have been removed. The logging is now using java.util.logging, no
				standard out or stanard error is used anymore.
			</action>
			<action type="update">
				Added utilty class for updating checksums
			</action>
			<action type="update">
				Added examples in utilities package for how to use new Header enumerations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="35">
				Builder pattern for the creation of cards introduced.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" issue="24">
				Fixed handling of binary tables built from an empty state row by row. Fixed coupling of binary
				tables and the FITS heap to allow copying of binary tables using the internal
				ColumnTable representation.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="23">
				Reorganized compression and added internal compression package.
			</action>
			<action type="remove" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="23">
				Tile compression, will be implemented from scratch in 2.0 and is not yet available in 1.13.0
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="29">
				Unit tests extended to cover 92% of the library .
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="17">
				Longstring support was improved and longer comments are now supported.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="20">
				Compression dependecy to apache compression is now optional again.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="12">
				When reading/writing the same card the comment moved one blank to the right.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="29">
				All javadoc's are now java-8 compatible and produce no warnings.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="15">
				Support for biginteger and bigdecimal.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="14">
				Generic detection of the value type of a card.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="7">
				Insert a header card at a specific position.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="36">
				All internally used keyword references are now enumerations.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="37">
				Comment mapping is now moved to the standard keyword enumeration.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub" issue="21">
				The settings of FitsFactory are now changeable to thread local specific settings.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.12.0" date="2015-02-20">
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Enumerations where added for ~1000 more or less Standard fits headers are now included (making compile references to headers possible).
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Moved the sources to github and the artifacts to the central repo.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Moved the license to maven as build system, incl reorganisation of the project. tests are no included in the published jars any more.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Moved the license to the official unlicensed.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Creation of a project site on github with issue management.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Java formatting/licence updating is now done by the maven plug ins.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="ritchieGitHub">
				Moved the code to Java 1.6 and @Override is now consistent.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				Richard van Nieuwenhoven joined the team.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.11.1" date="2014-07-07">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Debuggging statements inadverently left in V111.0 were removed.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.11.0" date="2013-06-07">
			<action type="fix" dev="Kevin McAbee">
				Fixed error in handling of strings with non-terminated quotes
				so that these don't crash program (thanks to Kevin McAbee)
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="Vincenzo Forchi">
				Deferred allocation of memory when creating
				FitsHeap's (thanks to Vincenzo Forchi, ESO).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="Pat Dowler">
				Fixed error in getting size of associated data for dummy
				headers in Header.getDataSize(). This could return 1 rather than 0 if
				NAXIS=0 was used to
				signal a
				dummy. This doesn't affect data
				when read normally (as full HDUs) since the ImageData class
				does the computation correctly. (Thanks to Pat Dowler, CADC)
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				The source code JAR (fits_src.jar) includes a number of new classes for
				which the corresponding class files are not included in fits.jar. These
				classes are
				pre-alpha versions of support for tile compressed data that
				is being developed. Interested Users may take a look at these, but they
				definitely are not expected to work
				today.
				Support for Rice, Gzip and
				HCompress compression is expected.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.10.0" date="2012-10-25">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				No functional changes to the FITS code are included in this release.
				All internal documentation has been updated to reflect that this library
				is
				now available
				in the public domain.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="1.08.1" date="2012-02-01">
			<action type="fix" dev="Jason Weiss">
				Fixed error in the writing of ASCII table columns where
				all of the elements of the table were null or 0 length
				strings. Previously we would write a
				column with
				TFORM A0.
				This is not supported by CFITSIO and since it is not
				valid Fortran is of dubious legality for FITS. Such columns
				are now written with A1 (issue noted by Jason
				Weiss,
				UCLA).
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				AsciiTable did not check if columns were of a valid type
				(if the FitsFactory methods were used, then a BinaryTable
				would be written, but a user can
				explicitly
				instantiate
				an AsciiTable). A FitsException is now returned if
				a column other than a String, double, int or long array is
				used
			</action>
		</release>


		<release version="1.07.0" date="2012-01-20">
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added
				boolean hadDuplicates()
				and
				List getDuplicates()
				methods to Header to allow users to track if there were
				duplicate keywords in a header.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.07.0" date="2011-11-11">
			<action type="update" dev="Booth Hartley">
				This release contains some new features suggested by Booth Hartley (IPAC) who supplied
				modified code including:
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Allow a FITS file to have invalid data after a valid FITS HDU.
				User can call FitsFactory.setAllowTerminalJunk(true) to enable
				this. The Fits
				object will return
				all valid HDUs. Note that
				whatever follows the valid FITS data must start with something
				that is clearly not FITs.
				This includes modifications to FitsFactory and
				Header.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Allow users to find original size of headers as they were
				read from some source file. The library throws away duplicate
				key values, so that the
				number of
				header cards in the header as read
				may be smaller than the original data. The getOriginalSize() gets
				the original size of the header in bytes. A resetOriginalSize()
				allows the
				user to tell the library that this header has been
				updated on disk and now has the same number of records as internally.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Fixed the order of the EXTEND keyword to follow the NAXISn keywords
				when it is specified. This constraint on the EXTEND keyword is
				no longer required
				in the
				latest version of the standard, but it
				doesn't hurt anything and may make the file more acceptable to some
				readers.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Fixed JavaDoc errors for a number of files.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Fixed a bug in Header.rewriteable() related to the same
				issue as the original size.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Updated Fits.setChecksum so that it will now set both
				the CHECKSUM and DATASUM keywords.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added tests for the new capabilities above and updated the
				checksum test.
			</action>
		</release>


		<release version="1.06.0" date="2011-05-23">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Substantial reworking of compression to accommodate
				BZIP2 compression. The Apache Bzip library is used or
				since this is very slow, the user can
				specify a local
				command to do the decompression using the BZIP_DECOMPRESSOR
				environment variable. This is assumed to require a
				'-' argument which is added if not supplied by the
				user.
				The
				decompressor should act as a filter between standard input
				and output.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				User compression flags are now completely
				ignored and the compression and the compression
				is determined entirely by the content of the stream.
				The
				Apache
				library will be needed in the
				classpath to accommodate BZIP2 inputs if the user
				does not supply the BZIP_DECOMPRESSOR.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Adding additional compression methods should be much easier and
				may only involve adding a couple of lines in the
				FitsUtil.decompress function if a
				decompressor
				class
				is available.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				One subtle consequence of how compression is now handled
				is that there is no advantage for users to
				create their own BufferedDataInputStream's.
				Users should
				just provide a standard input stream
				and allow the FITS library to wrap it in a
				BufferedDataInputStream.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="V. Forchi">
				A bug in the UndefinedData class was detected
				Vincenzo Forchi and has been corrected.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The nom.tam.util.AsciiFuncs class now handles
				ASCII encoding to more cleanly separate this
				functionality from the FITS library and to enable
				Java
				1.5
				compatibitity. (Suggested by changes of L.Bourges)
				Other V1.5 incompatiblities removed.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The HeaderCommentsMap class is now provided to enable
				users to control the comments that are generated in system
				generated header cards. The map
				is initialized
				to values
				that should be the same as the current defaults. This
				should allow users to emulate the comments of other packages.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				All Java code has been passed through NetBeans formatter
				so that it should have a more uniform appearance.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.05.1" date="2011-02-16">
			<action type="fix" dev="V. Forchi">The implementation of long string values was incorrect, using
				COMMENT rather than CONTINUE cards.noted originally by V. Forchi.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="V. Forchi">
				The placement of the header cursor after opening a primary array
				was such that unless the user took explicit action to move
				the cursor, new header
				records
				would be written before the
				EXTEND keyword which is a violation of the FITS standard (although
				it would not affect the operations of this library). The
				library now leaves
				the
				cursor just after the EXTEND keyword where
				new keywords are legal. It's still possible for users to write an
				illegal header but now it requires at
				least a little effort on
				their
				part.noted originally by V. Forchi.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				This build procedure for FITS library has been changed. The library is now stored
				as a NetBeans project and the standard NetBeans build script
				has been
				modified
				to generate the fits.jar and fits_src.jar. The names of a number of the test procedures
				have been slightly modified (XXXTester -> XXXTest) and test data are
				included in
				the class jar file.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.05.0" date="2010-12-12">
			<action type="update" dev="Laurent Bourges">
				Adding methods to allow finer control of the placement of
				metadata records for columns of FITS tables. This could previously
				be done using
				Cursors, but the
				TableHDU.setTableMeta() methods now
				allow these to be specified more directly.

				This involves changes only to TableHDU. Usage is illustrated in the test
				method
				BinaryTableTest.columnMetaTest.by Laurent Bourges
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="Laurent Bourges">
				Adding more rigor to the transformation between bytes and strings and
				fixing a bug in the handling of strings with embedded nuls. According
				to the
				standard an
				embedded null should terminate an string in a
				binary table.by Laurent Bourges

				The standard also precludes other non-printing characters from strings.
				This has been
				ignored
				previously, but there is now a method
				FitsFactory.setCheckAsciiString(boolean flag) which can be called
				to turn on checking. A warning will be
				issued and non-printing
				characters
				will be converted to spaces if this flag is set. Only a single
				warning will be issued regardless of the number of invalid characters are
				seen.

				There are changes in a
				number of
				classes where the conversions occur
				to ensure that the ASCII charset is used.

				How these changes work is illustrated in BinaryTableTest.specialStringsTest.by Laurent
				Bourges
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Handling fixed and variable length, single and double precision
				complex data. The library uses a float[2] or double[2]
				for a complex scalar.

				This
				is mostly bug
				fixes to existing code and changes are only
				in BinaryTable and BinaryTableHDU.

				The method BinaryTableHDU.setComplexColumn() allows the user to
				tell the FITS writer
				that a field
				which otherwise would be treated
				as a float or double array (with most rapidly varying
				dimensionality of 2) should be treated as complex.
				The internal
				data
				representations are
				identical.

				Variable length complex data will be found automatically if
				number of elements actually varies. A variable length complex
				column is a 3-D float or
				double array
				where the
				last dimension (for Java) is always 2, the first
				dimension is the number of rows in the table and the middle
				dimension is the number of complex numbers in
				the row and may
				vary
				from row to row. Other variable length columns are
				represented as 2-D arrays, where the first index points to the
				row, and the second index enumerates the
				elements in the row.

				Use of complex columns is illustrated in BinaryTableTest in the routines
				testSimpleComplex (fixed columns), testVar (variable length
				columns), and
				buildByColumn and buildByRow
				where columns
				and rows containing complex numbers are added to existing
				tables.by Laurent Bourges
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Changing the null HDU created when a table is to be written without
				a prior image to use a vector with dimensionality 0 rather than
				a
				one-dimensional vector
				with a dimension of 0. I.e, use
				NAXIS=0 rather than NAXIS=1, NAXIS1=0.by Laurent Bourges
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Consolidating the writing of padding at the end of FITS elements into
				the FitsUtil.pad methods.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Adding the reset() method to the FitsElement interface. This attempts
				to reset the Fits input stream pointer to the beginning of the element.
				It
				does not throw
				exceptions but will return false if not successful.
				This is intended to make it easier for user who wish to use low-level
				I/O to read FITS data, by allowing them to
				position the
				stream to the
				beginning of the data they are interested in.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Changed FitsUtil.HDUFactory(Object x) to accept a Header object as well
				as the various kinds of data inputs.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Provided a method in BinaryTable to get back the ModelRow array.
				This makes is easier for users to do low level I/O in binary tables.
				An
				ArrayDataInput object
				will read a row of the table, given the
				result of getModelRow().
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added a getColumns() method to TableHDU. This returns an Object[] array
				where each entry is the result of getColumn(n)
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.04.0" date="2009-12-24">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Support for the HEASARC long strings convention has been added.
				This affects only the Header class. Two new public static methods
				have been added.
				setLongStringsEnabled(boolean)
				allows the use to enable/disable the handling of long strings.
				getLongStringsEnabled()
				returns the current setting. By default long strings are
				disabled.
				The convention is enabled automatically whenever a header is read
				which has the LONGSTRN keyword is read. It is not disabled if subsequent
				headers are read which do not
				have this keyword. The
				addValue(String,String,String), getStringValue(String) and removeCard(String)
				methods are affected, allowing the user to set, read and delete long string
				values. The library does NOT ensure that users do not interpolate new keywords
				or comments inside the card sequence that is used to store the long
				string value.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				A bug in the processing of keyword values with embedded apostrophes was fixed.
				Apostrophe's were properly doubled in encoding but the doubling was
				left
				when
				the values were read.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="Mark Taylor">
				A potential bug in the processing of headers discovered by Mark Taylor was fixed.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.03.1" date="2009-07-27">
			<action type="add" dev="J.C. Segovia">
				The implementation of the FitsUtil.byteArrayToStrings method was changed
				so that trimmed space from strings can be cleaned up more efficiently.
				Change
				suggested by J.C. Segovia (ESA).
				There should be no effect -- other than memory usage -- on external programs.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Users might want to note that when reading string values in binary tables,
				both leading and trailing spaces are trimmed from the string values.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.03.0" date="2009-07-22">
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				This release adds further support for large datasets where the size of
				an HDU may exceed 2GB. In ArrayDataInput (and the BufferedFile
				and
				BufferedDataInputStream that implement it)
				int skipBytes(int)
				method of java.io.DataInput is now overloaded with
				long skipBytes(long).

				In ArrayFuncs
				int computeSize(Object)
				method is
				augmented with
				long computeLSize(Object)
				It was not possible to use the same name here since the argument type
				is the same.
				Similarly
				int nElements(Object)
				is now
				matched with
				long
				nLElements(Object)

				These changes should not affect current usage of the existing methods.

				References to skipBytes and computeSize in the FITS classes now take
				advantage of these
				new methods.

				While these changes increase the support of the library for large datasets,
				there are still a number of restictions that arise from Java's limit that
				array indices
				must be ints. E.g., no single dimension can exceed 2 GB,
				and the total size of the heap for a given binary table HDU cannot
				exceed 2
				GB. ASCII tables may also be limited to 2 GB
				in some circumstances.
				Files which exceed these limits may be readable using line by line
				approaches, but users will need to use the library at a much lower level.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				The Header.read() method may now throw an IOException in circumstances
				where it would previously throw an Error. It probably should throw
				a
				FitsException, but
				that was not in the signature and might have broken
				existing programs.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				A bug in the new PaddingException was fixed which allows use of Tilers
				with truncated Image HDUs.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Some obsolete comments indicating that BITPIX=64 was an extension of
				FITS were deleted. FITS has officially supported longs for a fair number
				of
				years now.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The regression tests have been augmented to test the new features, but users
				should note that the new BigFileTester test takes a very long time
				to run. E.g.,
				on the primary development machine this takes 240 seconds while all of the
				other tests finish in just a few seconds. The time is simply the time it
				takes to write a
				file of known
				content that is more than 2 GB in size.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.02.0" date="2009-07-08">
			<action type="update" dev="L. Michel">
				ASCII tables with data fields that were blank filled were not being handled properly.
				According to the FITS standards, numeric fields where the
				FITS table has
				blanks are
				to be treated as containing 0. A parsing error was being returned. The getInt, getLong,
				and getDouble methods in ByteParser were changed to acoommodate
				this case
				(getFloat simply
				calls getDouble).suggested by L. Michel
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				A new exception, PaddingException, which inherits from FitsException has been added.
				This exception is thrown when an otherwise valid HDU is not
				properly
				padded to the next
				2880 byte boundary. The exception class has a getTruncatedHDU method which allows the
				user to get the information in the truncated HDU. In addition to
				the new
				class changes were
				made in BinaryTable, AsciiTable, UndefinedData, ImageData and RandomGroupsData to throw the
				exception at the appropriate
				time. The main Fits method was
				also
				updated so that when
				its readHDU() method is being used, the notional header that is given to the truncated HDU
				in the Data classes is replaced by the actual header. If a
				user
				wishes to ignore padding
				exceptions, then a FITS file may be read using the following idiom in the new nom.tam.fits.test.PaddingTester to see a complete example
				of this
				idiom.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.01.0" date="2009-06-24">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				A number of changes were implemented to handle large FITS files more
				gracefully and to correct bugs associated with large files. This includes
				a
				change to the
				method
				Data.getTrueSize();
				This method was public only for the BinaryTable data type and previously
				returned an int. It now returns a long. User programs which called
				this
				method
				will need to be recompiled.
				Specific bugs were noted by Javier Diaz and Juan Carlos Segovia.
				Note that the program may still fail on very
				large files but it should give
				more
				informative error messages when it does so
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">A bug noted by Thomas Granzer in the handling of HIERARCH keyword values
				was also corrected.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.00.2" date="2009-03-09">
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Fixed bug where reading a table by rows caused reading
				a subsequent HDU to fail. Added tests to BinaryTableTester and
				HeaderCardTester.
			</action>
		</release>


		<release version="1.00.1" date="2009-02-19">
			<action type="fix" dev="Javier Diaz">
				Fixed bug where exponential notation in FITS header keywords used 'e' rather than 'E' (noted by Javier Diaz)
			</action>
		</release>


		<release version="1.00.0.1" date="2008-07-11">
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">The major chage to this release is support for .Z compressed images.
				A problem reading past the end of files in normal FITS processing was included
				in the 1.0
				release and was fixed (7/11/08). The earlier jars were overwritten.
				The problem shows up in the regression test suite.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="1.00.0" date="2008-06-10">
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">The major chage to this release is support for .Z compressed images.
				This is implemented by using the uncompress command which must
				be in the user's
				execution
				path.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">There is much more dynamic checking of the magic number of inputs
				to determine whether the input to the FITS constructor is compressed
				or not, and
				if
				compressed what the compression type is.
				This can still be confused but in many cases it will get the
				compression right regardless of what the user specifies.
				Future versions
				may
				completely ignore the user specified compression
				flag.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="A. Kovacs">Bug fix to BinaryTable by A. Kovacs
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.99.3" date="2007-12-04">
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Binary table handling of 1 character strings.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.99.5" date="2007-12-04">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added Support HTTPS, FTP and FILE URLs
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added Fits(String,compressed) constructor
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Made some of the methods in FitsFactory public.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added getRawElement method to Binary table.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Changed handling of double values in header
				so that they all fit into the fixed format.
				In rare circumstances this may result in a loss
				of
				precision.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Additional fixes for zero length and null strings
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="A. Kovacs">
				Fix to handling of Strings in Binary tables (A. Kovacs)
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.99.3" date="2006-12-21">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Additional changes to handle null and zero length strings.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.99.2" date="2006-12-15">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Moved code to use subversion repository and Ant compile scripts.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Major transformations of all test code to use Junit and automated
				checking rather than comparing print outs.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				nom.tam.fits.utilities package created and FitsCopy and FitsReader
				classes were moved there.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				A few test classes, e.g., BigImage and RMFUpdTest were deleted and
				their functions subsumed into the other tests.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Test routines now considered standard part of library. There
				are not separate JARs for the test routines.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Note that the test routines use Annotations and may not compile
				with versions of Java prior to 1.5.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				ArrayFuncs: Added arrayEquals() methods which allow comparison
				of arrays of arbitrary dimensionality. Used extensively
				in the updated test classes.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				AsciiTable: Setting a row, column or element de-nulls any
				elements that were set to null.
				Fixed offsets in columns after column was deleted.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				FitsUtil: Fixed bug in maxLength which looked for nulls in
				the array pointer rather than the individual strings.
				Added check for nulls in
				stringsToByteArray
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				HeaderCard: Truncated String in one argument constructor to
				a maximum of 80 characters.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				BinaryTable: Fixed handling of columns with 0 width (e.g.,
				0 length strings, or arrays of 0 length.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				ColumnTable: Fixed handling of columns with 0 width.
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.99.1" date="2006-07-29">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Added new methods to delete rows and columns from both binary and ASCII tables.
				There are changes to many of the table classes including
				util/ColumnTable.
				These changes were suggested by row deletion code written by R. Mathar,
				but the actual implementation is entirely independent and errors
				are handled somewhat
				differently than in
				his code. There are deleteColumns
				and deleteRows methods in TableHDU that delete either a specified range
				or all tables or columns after
				(and including) the
				one specified.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The util.HashedList implementation has been completely revised. It now
				uses a HashedMap for keyed access and an ArrayList for sequential access.
				It no longer
				implements a simple but custom list structure. The public
				interface was not significantly changed.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				Header now sorts keywords before a header is written to ensure that
				required keywords come where they need to be. Previously users
				needed to work
				to make sure
				that they wrote required keywords
				in the right location in the header. A new class, HeaderOrder,
				is used.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				A number of errors in the handling of variable length arrays were
				fixed. These were pointed out by Guillame Belanger. This included
				changes to
				util.ColumnTable
				but mostly BinaryTable and FitsHeap.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="R.J. Mathar">
				A number of changes mostly to BinaryTable or documentation in other
				routines suggested by R. MAthar.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.99.0" date="2006-06-23">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The three packages, nom.tam.fits, nom.tam.util and nom.tam.image
				have been combined into a single JAR file for the convenience
				of the user.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="R.J. Mathar">
				Added support for Checksums. Use the setChecksum methods in the
				FITS class to add checksums to FITS HDUs. The static method
				setChecksum(HDU) adds a
				checksum to
				a given HDU. The instance
				method setChecksum() adds checksums to all HDUs in the file.
				Note that setting the checksum should be the last step before
				writing the file
				since any
				manipulation of the file is likely
				to invalidate the checksum.
				(This code was contributed by R.J. Mathar, Leiden University).
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				Changed handling of 1-d arrays with a single element so that
				they can be distinguished from scalar values. No TDIM will be
				be created for scalar
				columns, and a
				TDIMn = '(1)' will give
				an array rather than a scalar value. (Suggested by Jorgo Bakker. ESA)
				For data written using the previous version of the FITS library,
				this
				may cause
				problems when the data is read with the new version,
				since the type of the returned column will be different.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="Laurent Michel">
				When checking if a file is compressed, the actual content of the
				file will be used if possible rather than the name (Suggested by Laurent Michel,
				CDS)
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="Laurent Michel">
				The code used to support TFORMn = 'xNNN' where the array dimension followed rather
				than preceded the format type. This has been deleted
				(Suggested by Laurent
				Michel, CDS)
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="Fred Romelfanger and Jorgo Bakker">
				Zero-length string values should now be allowed as header keyword values
				(Bug noted by Fred Romelfanger, ST ScI and Jorgo Bakker, ESA).
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The addLine methods in Header are now public rather than protected.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				If the Fits.write() method is called using a BufferedFile, then the size of the
				file is truncated at the end of the write. Otherwise if the FITS
				data was
				being written into a previously existing file of greater length, there
				would be extra bytes at the end of the file. This is still possible
				if the user uses the write
				methods for
				individual constituents of the FITS
				object.
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				The ArrayFuncs.newInstance method now accepts an dimension array of length
				0 and returns a 1-d array of length 1 to emulate a scalar.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Corrected bug in writing a binary table when the read of that table
				had been deferred.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.97" date="2003-11-01">
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">
				Version 0.97 corrects several bugs in the handling header
				keywords and ASCII tables and Images.
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				The HeaderCard class now has constructor
				with the signature (String,String,boolean) which
				may be used to generate either a comment style
				card with
				the keyword
				and value
				given, or a card with a null value
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">The handling of the EXTEND keyword has been made consistent
				with FITS standards
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">ASCII tables are first read to an intermediate byte
				buffer and then parsed as needed. Bugs where this
				buffer was being deleted at inappropriate
				times, or
				left
				undeleted when it was invalid were fixed.
				This should fix errors when AsciiTables are read
				from non-seekable sources. This should slightly
				speed up most access to
				ASCII tables
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">In certain circumstances an Image would not be
				properly initialized before it was to be written
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">The routines Header, HeaderCard, ImageData and AsciiTableData
				where modified in this release
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">
				The getChannel method was added to BufferedFile
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.96" date="2003-03-20">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">The handling of PCOUNT, GCOUNT and EXTEND keywords
				was changed in images so that the first two
				are only generated for extensions and the first
				only for primary
				HDU's.
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">A bug in the creation of ASCII Table Headers was fixed.
				Some of the header cards in the header were being
				inserted as if they were comments, allowing
				multiple
				copies to be generated.
				This was also possible when a Header was created
				from an array of strings.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.93" date="2001-01-01">
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">The HeaderCard class has been modified to handle
				The HIERARCH keyword convention. The FitsFactory
				now has methods set/getUseHierarch to
				enable/disable this
				processing
			</action>
			<action type="add" dev="tmcglynn">A new interface FitsElement has been added which
				is implemented by the BasicHDU, Header, Data and FitsHeap
				classes. It enables users to more easily
				deal with
				FITS data
				at the byte level. There is also a public method
				getDataSize in Header to get the size in bytes
				of the associated data element including padding.
				The FitsHeap
				class has
				been made public
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="Jens Knudstrup">Several bugs relating to null images were corrected.
				(Thanks to Jens Knudstrup) (ImageData)
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">The handling of EOF conditions in array reads in
				the BufferedFile and BufferedDataInputStream classes
				was made consistent with the behavior of
				java.io classes
				reading byte arrays
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">Several bug fixes implemented by Alan Brighton (and already
				fixed in the Jsky distribution) were incorporated
			</action>
			<action type="fix" dev="tmcglynn">All references to the java.lang.reflect.Array.newInstance()
				methods were modified to use new methods with the same signature
				in ArrayFuncs. These new
				methods
				throw an OutOfMemory exception
				when an array cannot be created. The JVM methods seem -- in
				contradiction to the documentation -- to simply return null.
				Previously the
				program
				could mysteriously crash when used to read large
				files, when the null in a dynamic allocation was eventually
				dereferenced
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.92" date="2000-10-12">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				BinaryTable
				Fixed bug initializing BinaryTable's read from streams
				(rather than files)
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.91" date="1996-01-02">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">
				FitsDate:
				added getFitsDateString
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Header:
				FitsDate:
				made several methods public
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn"> added checking for initial keywords before write</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">BinaryTable:
				removed TDIM keywords for variable length columns
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">BinaryTable:
				fixed bug that made BinaryTable(Object[][]) constructor
				unusable
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">BinaryTableHDU:
				fixed usage of THEAP keyword
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">AsciiTable:
				use blanks for data filler rather than nulls
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">BasicHDU
				made getDummyHDU public
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">HeaderCard
				fixed padding of string values which
				sometimes had one too many spaces
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">image.ImageTiler
				allow requests for tiles that
				are not fully within the original image
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">util.ByteFormatter:
				changed formatter to use 'E' (rather than 'e')
				for exponents since 'e' not legal for
				FITS ASCII tables
			</action>
		</release>

		<release version="0.90" date="1996-01-01">
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Support for ASCII tables</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Deferred input for images and tables (data is read
				only when user actually requests it)
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Image subsetting without reading the entire image</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Reading individual rows and elements of tables without
				reading the entire table
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Support for in-place rewriting of headers and data</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Transparent support for Strings in ASCII and Binary tables</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Transparent support for booleans in binary tables, including
				varying length columns
			</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">Efficient buffered random access methods</action>
			<action type="update" dev="tmcglynn">More flexible support for I/O of primitive arrays</action>
		</release>

	</body>
</document>
